{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A “requiem” titled for this battle states “What like a bullet can undeceive,” and was written by Herman Melville. Ambrose Bierce described “What I Saw of [this battle]” in an 1874 short story. At this battle, Lew Wallace, the author of Ben-Hur, led a division that marched along the Shunpike Road due to confusion in their battle orders. For ten points, name this Civil War battle fought in Tennessee near Pittsburg Landing.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Shiloh",
        "Shiloh: A Requiem",
        "Battle of Pittsburg Landing before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader of this country lost international support after caning students who protested mandatory uniforms; that man, who spent 30 million dollars on a Napoleonic coronation, came to power in this country’s Saint-Sylvestre coup, overthrowing David Dacko. Seleka rebels founded the Republic of Langone in this former French colony, which is currently ruled by Faustin-Archange Touadera. Jean-Bedel Bokassa once ruled, for ten points, what African country with capital at Bangui?",
      "answer": "Central African Republic"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman mentored Marie Zakrzewska, who helped grow her dispensary at Tompkins Square into an institution that merged with New York Presbyterian in 2013. After receiving backlash from the United States Sanitary Commission, this woman helped establish the Women’s Central Relief Association during the Civil War. Charles Lee bowed to this woman in 1849 while granting her a degree earned after 150 students unanimously agreed to accept her admittance at Geneva College. For ten points, name this first woman to obtain an American medical degree.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "French traders are considered the first Europeans to have explored this area’s St. Francois and Boston Mountains. This region’s White and Osage Rivers were dammed by the US Army Corps of Engineers in 1911 to create several new lakes, and its Mark Twain National Forest was restored by the Civilian Conservation Corps in the 1930s. The Whitewater scandal concerned land development in, for ten points, what mountainous plateau primarily located in northern Arkansas and southern Missouri?",
      "answer": [
        "the Ozarks",
        "Ozark Mountains",
        "Ozark Plateau"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this war, the USS Essex and USS Essex Junior were captured off the coast of Chile. One side in this war ambushed a convoy at Henderson Bay which led to the Second Battle of Sacket’s Harbor. In an 1882 book, Theodore Roosevelt says the American navy gave the populace confidence in the face of an ineffectual army during this war. Fort Niagara was captured in, for ten points, what war in which Oliver Hazard Perry won the Battle of Lake Erie?",
      "answer": "War of 1812"
    },
    {
      "question": "Eugene Schuyler created a report of atrocities in this country. In this country, the Batak Massacre was caused by Bashi-Bazouks during the April Uprising. By the Treaty of San Stefano, this country was liberated from Ottoman Rule by Russia in 1878, but its northern neighbor gained Dobruja. William Gladstone denounced the “horrors” of this country in his Midlothian Campaign. Simeon II was the last Tsar of, for ten points, what Balkan nation north of Greece that is ruled from Sofia?",
      "answer": "Bulgaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group established October 16th as the Day of Atonement, on which men would refrain from engaging in activity harmful to their families. The beliefs of this group, collected in the book The Supreme Wisdom, tell of how Yakub created a race of evil people on the island of Patmos. A leader of this group, Louis Farrakhan, organized the Million Man March on Washington in 1995. For ten points, name this African-American religious group that adopted traditions of the prophet Muhammad.",
      "answer": [
        "Nation of Islam",
        "NOI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Raymond de Sauvetˆat was the first leader of a school of translators based in this city during the Middle Ages. Eleanor, a noblewoman from this city, became known as the Grand Duchess of Tuscany after marrying Cosimo I [the first] de Medici. This city, whose swords were once seen as the finest in Europe, is home to the Synagogue of El Transito in its Jewish quarter. Holy Roman Emperor Charles V ruled mainly from this Castilian city. For ten points, name this “Imperial City” in Spain.",
      "answer": "Toledo , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer dramatized the destruction of Missolonghi during the Greek War of Indepenedence in his opera The Siege of Corinth. This composer repeated musical phrases in a namesake crescendo; that technique is employed in pieces like the overture to The Thieving Magpie. A galop known as “The March of the Swiss Soldiers” concludes the overture to this man’s final opera, which depicts a Swiss folk hero who shoots an apple off his son’s head. For ten points, name this Italian composer of William Tell.",
      "answer": "Gioachino Rossini"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first of these works urges caution, stating that “Nothing valuable can be lost by taking time,” before claiming that the “better angels of our nature” will once again stir the “mystic chords of memory.” One of these speeches quotes Matthew 18:7, saying “Woe unto the world because of offences,” and calls slavery one of those offenses. The second of these speeches advises action “With malice toward none, with charity for all.” For ten points, name these speeches delivered in 1861 and 1865 in Washington, DC.",
      "answer": "Abraham Lincoln’s Inaugural Addresses"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The generals Mundus and Mauricius died fighting this group at Salona. Boethius was executed for trying to kill a king of this group, who was served by Cassiodorus. At the Battle of Taginae, Narses killed Totila, a ruler of this group. The Lombards invaded the Byzantine Empire shortly after Justinian conquered this group. A ruler of these people, Theodoric, killed Odoacer and established a new capital city. Belisarius took Rome from, for ten points, what group of eastern Goths?",
        "answer": "Ostrogoths"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This northern Italian city became the Ostrogoth capital after Theodoric killed Odoacer. It was later a Byzantine exarchate and the center of Lombard power.",
        "answer": "Ravenna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man secured power after hiring North Korea to train the paramilitary Fifth Brigade, which he used to purge political enemies during the Gukurahundi period. This man’s removal of vice president EmersonMnangagwaledtospeculationthatheplannedtonamehisunpopularwifeGraceashissuccessor, leading to his removal in a 2017 coup. This man’s reign was marked by an inflation rate that peaked at 100,000 percent in 2008. For ten points, name this longtime ruler of Zimbabwe.",
        "answer": "Robert Mugabe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mugabe rose to prominence in a civil war against this man, who issued the Unilateral Declaration of Independence.",
        "answer": "Ian Smith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The creation of this regime is remembered by a nationwide sounding of air raid sirens every September 18th. The Lytton Commission was established by the United Nations to investigate the creation of this state, which was founded after a failed dynamite attack on a railway track was used as a pretext for the Kwantung Army to launch an invasion. The Mukden Incident led to the establishment of this state, which installed Pu Yi as emperor. For ten points, name this Japanese puppet state installed in Manchuria.",
        "answer": "Manchukuo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Manchukuo’s attempts to expand into the Soviet Union were thwarted at this series of battles in Mongolia, where Georgi Zhukov commanded the Soviet forces. The first of these battles took place in May 1939.",
        "answer": [
          "Battles of Khalkhin Gol",
          "Battles of the Khalkh River",
          "Khalkha River"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While led by Donald Fehr, one of these organizations accused Peter Ueberroth of inciting collusion; that organization of this type was earlier led by Marvin Miller, who worked to nullify the reserve clause in the fight for free agency. An attempt to create one of these organizations at Northwestern University was blocked by the NLRB in 2015, and another one of these organizations was recertified by Roger Goodell after a 2011 lockout. For ten points, name these organizations that represent athletes in collective bargaining.",
        "answer": [
          "labor unions in sports",
          "answers related to professional baseball unions throughout",
          "answers related to amateur and/or college football unions after Northwestern is read",
          "answers related to professional football unions after “Goodell” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Major League Baseball’s reserve clause was challenged by Curt Flood and the union in a 1972 Supreme Court case; this justice wrote a lengthy history of baseball in the majority opinion. This man’s other majority opinions include Roe v. Wade.",
        "answer": "Harry Blackmun"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This treaty required one signatory to cancel Article 27 of its constitution, which guaranteed reparations of land to indigenous people. As a result, this treaty was publicly attacked in the Lacandon Jungle Declaration by a group led by the ski-mask wearing Subcomandante Marcos, the Zapatistas. Carlos Salinas de Gortari and Brian Mulroney were key negotiators of this treaty, which was described as causing a “giant sucking sound” by Ross Perot in a debate against Al Gore. For ten points, name this 1992 trade agreement signed by Canada, Mexico, and the US.",
        "answer": "North American Free Trade Agreement or NAFTA"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to NAFTA’s provisions on agriculture, the US had recruited these Mexican laborers to work on farms under a program that lasted from 1942 to 1964.",
        "answer": "braceros"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure fought Francesco Maria I in the War of Urbino to secure his nephew’s rule over the city. This man received the embassy of the Portuguese king Manuel I, who had previously gifted this man an elephant named Hanno. This man presided over the closing of the Fifth Lateran Council and issued the papal bull Exsurge Domine [ex-oor-gay doh-mee-nay] in condemnation of the author of the 95 Theses. For ten points, name this pope who clashed with Martin Luther.",
        "answer": [
          "Pope Leo X",
          "Giovanni di Lorenzo de’ Medici"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leo considered, but never carried out, a crusade against this Ottoman sultan, whose expansion into Western Europe was continued by his son Suleiman the Magnificent.",
        "answer": [
          "Selim I",
          "Selim the Grim",
          "Selim the Resolute"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This project was spurred on by a 1986 conference led by Charles DeLisi in Santa Fe. The Celera Corporation, founded by Craig Venter, competed with this project using a “shotgun” technique and saw its stock price crash after President Clinton announced patents on this project’s findings would not be granted. Francis Collins and James Watson were leaders of, for ten points, what project, the world’s largest collaborative biological research project, that created a mosaic-like mapping of the sequence of human DNA in the 1990s?",
        "answer": "Human Genome Project or HGP"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This scientist invented a namesake type of sequencing that was initially used by the Human Genome Project, for which he received his second Nobel Prize in Chemistry. This man also determined the primary structure of insulin.",
        "answer": "Frederick Sanger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Heavy fire during this battle destroyed a 22-inch tree trunk whose stump is now housed at the Smithsonian. One side in this battle sprung an unsuccessful ambush at Harris Farm before retreating. During this battle, several failed attacks on Laurel Hill led one side to instead target Mule Shoe, where Horatio Wright’s continued attacks led the shoe to become known as the “Bloody Angle.” The bloodiest battle of the Overland Campaign was, for ten points, what two-week long battle in Virginia in May 1864, shortly after the Battle of the Wilderness?",
        "answer": "Battle of Spotsylvania Courthouse"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Union general was killed at Spotsylvania Courthouse shortly after disparaging the abilities of Confederate snipers, claiming they “couldn’t hit an elephant at this distance.” He was the highest ranking Union death in the Civil War.",
        "answer": "John Sedgwick"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Antebellum Disputes over Slavery",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Bleeding” state that co-names an 1854 act with Nebraska.",
          "answer": "Bleeding Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-slavery crusader who committed the Pottawatomie Massacre and raided Harper’s Ferry.",
          "answer": "John Brown"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, known as “Old Rough and Ready,” whose death led to the passage of the Compromise of 1850.",
          "answer": "Zachary Taylor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept, supported by Stephen Douglas, that states that the people of a state should decide if they want slavery.",
          "answer": "popular sovereignty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-slavery political party for whom Martin Van Buren unsuccessfully ran in 1848.",
          "answer": "Free Soil Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposal that would have banned slavery in land acquired in the Mexican-American War.",
          "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
        },
        {
          "question": "1850 “bloodhound” law that was briefly ruled unconstitutional in Wisconsin, until the case of Abelman v. Booth.",
          "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "Client of Robert Morris whose conviction under that act triggered a “vile procession” of 50,000 marchers in Boston.",
          "answer": "Anthony Burns"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Crimea",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Great” Russian empress who annexed the Crimea in 1783.",
          "answer": "Catherine the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean city where Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin met in a 1945 conference.",
          "answer": "Yalta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottoman sultan who annexed the Crimean Khanate in 1475.",
          "answer": "Mehmed the Conqueror or Mehmed II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean War nurse who became known as “the Lady with the Lamp” and modernized war nursing practices",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "HIghest British honor, created during the Crimean War, whose medals are legendary made from stolen Crimean cannon.",
          "answer": "Victoria Cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that was the subject of a year-long Franco-British siege during the Crimean War.",
          "answer": "Siege of Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean War battle during that siege that inspired Tennyson’s “Charge of the Light Brigade.”",
          "answer": "Battle of Balaclava"
        },
        {
          "question": "Field Marshal whose Highlanders formed the Thin Red Line in that battle.",
          "answer": "Colin Campbell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apartheid",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Party led by Nelson Mandela that took over South Africa’s government after the fall of apartheid.",
          "answer": [
            "African National Congress",
            "ANC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language spoken, alongside English, by South Africa’s formerly dominant white minority.",
          "answer": "Afrikaans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bantu ethnic group that, along with the Zulu, made up most of South Africa’s black majority.",
          "answer": [
            "Xhosa , with a lateral click at the start",
            "be lenient"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President who brokered the end of apartheid and shared the Nobel Peace Prize with Mandela.",
          "answer": "Fredrik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island on which Mandela was imprisoned for 27 years.",
          "answer": "Robben Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial at which Nelson Mandela gave his “I am prepared to die” speech.",
          "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant anti-apartheid group, the armed wing of Mandela’s political party, that formed in 1961.",
          "answer": "Spear of the Nation or Umkhonto we Sizwe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Farm where Mandela hid while being pursued by police.",
          "answer": "Lilliesleaf Farm"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This philosopher’s idea that a human being consists merely of its properties and nothing intrinsically substantive is known as his “bundle theory.” This philosopher stirred up controversy by praising polytheism and suggesting it led to monotheistic religions in his (20 pts)",
        "Natural History of Religion. A law named after this man states that thinkers commit a fallacy when they move from positive to normative statements and is called his (10 pts)",
        "“is-ought problem.” For ten points, name this Scottish philosopher who wrote An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding."
      ],
      "answer": "David Hume"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A few former members of this group gathered intelligence as part of the Kit Carson Scouts. The book People’s War, People’s Army is described as this group’s “Insurrection Manual for (20 pts)",
        "Underdeveloped Countries” and was written by a general who aided both his army and this group with supplies along the Truong Son trail. This group, which was targeted by the Strategic (10 pts)",
        "Hamlet Program, attempted to expand into the Mekong Delta following the Tet Offensive. For ten points, name these communist guerrillas in South Vietnam."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Viet Cong or the National Liberation Front for Southern Vietnam",
        "the People’s Liberation Armed Forces of South Vietnam",
        "the PLAF"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Sich autonomous state was created for these people in the Treaty of Pereyaslav, which was signed in the wake of the Khmelnytsky [k’mel-nit-skee] uprising against Polish- Lithuanian control. These people extended their reach to the (20 pts)",
        "Terek and Yaik after allying with government forces, but their ranks also included rebellious leaders like Stenka Razin and Yemelyan (10 pts)",
        "Pugachev. This group was predominantly centered around the Dnieper and Don rivers. For ten points, name these autonomous horsemen who served as police and military units in 19th century Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Cossacks"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A turning point in this period was the Battle of Naissus; a cavalry commander at that battle later defeated the Palmyrenes, a breakaway empire that formed during this period. Postumus’s Gallic Empire was also defeated by Aurelian near the end of this period, which began with the (20 pts)",
        "Year of the Six Emperors and ended with the rule of Diocletian. Numerous generals took the imperial throne during this period, in which economic (10 pts)",
        "breakdown ruined life on the frontier. For ten points, name this century in which the Roman Empire nearly fell completely apart."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Crisis of the Third Century AD",
        "CE"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Mitchell, Frank Morrison and this man were placed in contempt after marking Buck Stove and Range Company on an “unfair list.” This man worked with Adolph Strasser to form a trade union whose members included his successor, William (20 pts)",
        "Green. One organization this man founded pressed for immigration quotas like the Emergency Quota Act. This man called for (10 pts)",
        "“pure and simple unionism” opposing political party influence in trade unions. For ten points, name this former cigar maker who founded the American Federation of Labor, or AFL."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel Gompers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Women’s Death Battalion supported this man against a 1917 coup by his enemies. This man gained fame reporting on the Lena Goldfields Massacre. This Trudovik names an offensive against Austria-Hungary that is also called the July Offensive. After the (20 pts)",
        "Kornilov affair, this man became Commander in Chief; earlier, he replaced Prince Lvov as Prime Minister. A movement against this man called for (10 pts)",
        "“peace, land and bread” and led to the October Revolution. For ten points, name this leader of the Russian Provisional Government who was ousted by the Bolsheviks under Lenin."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander Kerensky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Richie claimed that this country’s early films were limited by a live narrator whose comments caused directors to be too subtle. A director from this country commented on its post-war economy in a film where a woman is accused of stealing money to buy a (20 pts)",
        "washing machine. In another film from this country, the title warriors defend a rural village from bandits after being united by (10 pts)",
        "Kambei. This country relied more on Western film after its domestic production was disrupted by the 1923 Great Kanto earthquake. For ten points, name this country where Akira Kurosawa created Seven Samurai."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Japan",
        "Nippon",
        "Nihon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wei Zheng [“way” zhun] advised this dynasty’s second emperor, Li Shimin [lee sh-ming], also known as Taizong [“tie”-zohn]. The Silla kingdom unified Korea against opposition from this dynasty, whose forces gave up the secret to making (20 pts)",
        "paper after being defeated by Muslim troops at the Talas River. This dynasty’s rule was interrupted by the brief Zhou Dynasty, led by Wu Zetian [woo zuh-tehn], China’s only female emperor. (10 pts)",
        "An Lushan [ahn loo-shahn] launched a revolt against, for ten points, what dynasty that followed the Sui [swee] and ruled during China’s golden age from the 7th to the 10th century?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    }
  ]
}